<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Source Themes | Emanuele Dicarlo</title>
    <link>/tag/source-themes/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/source-themes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Source Themes</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon.png</url>
      <title>Source Themes</title>
      <link>/tag/source-themes/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>How do Firms adjust to Negative Labor Supply Shocks? Evidence form Migration Outflows (Job Market Paper)</title>
      <link>/workinprogress/0migration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/workinprogress/0migration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Adjustments of firms to large labor outflows have important implications for the performance of firms and for job opportunities of workers. This paper studies adjustments of Italian firms to negative labor supply shocks in the context of workers&amp;rsquo; outflows from Italy to Switzerland. My Diff-in-Diff leverages the implementation of a policy in which Switzerland grated free labor market mobility to EU citizens and different treatment intensity of Italian firms based on the distance to the Swiss border. Using detailed social security data on the universe of Italian firms and workers I document large outflows of workers and fewer surviving firms in the treatment group. Despite replacing workers and becoming more capital intensive, treated firms are less productive and have a lower wage growth.
I explain this puzzle through the lens of a simple model of imperfect substitutability of workers and provide suggestive evidence that high-skill intensive firms face a tighter market for high skilled labor and drive the negative results on productivity and wage growth, while low-skill intensive firms do not suffer productivity losses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Season in Hell: Italy’s Debt Recovery after the Financial Crises (joint with P. Rizza and P. Tommasino)</title>
      <link>/workinprogress/2bdi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/workinprogress/2bdi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Skill Content of Occupations across Low and Middle Income Countries: Evidence from Harmonized Data</title>
      <link>/otherwork/0wb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/otherwork/0wb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Using new and harmonized worker-level survey data on tasks at work in the developing
world, this paper constructs, for the first time, a measure of the skill content of occupations
for 10 low and middle-income countries. Following Autor, Levy and Murnane (2003),
Acemoglu and Autor (2011), and Autor and Handel (2013), we map tasks into non-routine
analytical, non-routine interpersonal, and routine &amp;amp; manual skill groups. We find significant
differences in the skill mix used by workers across different occupations, with selected whitecollar occupations being intensive in Analytical and Interpersonal skills, while others— mostly
blue collar, but not only— being more intensive in Routine and Manual skills. We also find
that the rankings of occupations along the skill dimensions are quite stable across countries,
and they correlate significantly higher between middle- and low-income countries than
between them and the United States. Hence, the common practice of assuming the same
skill structure for occupations in the United States and other countries can be misleading.
Finally, we find that the heterogeneity of skill content between occupations (within countries)
tends to decrease with the level of income, while the heterogeneity within occupations
decreases only weakly (or not at all) for higher income levels. Taken together, these results
suggest that as countries develop, they tend to adopt and use certain skills more widely,
especially across occupations. This may suggest some degree of specialization in skills
content of tasks as countries develop, especially moving towards less occupation-specific
Analytical or Interpersonal skills that are becoming increasingly relevant across the board.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example journal article</title>
      <link>/publication/journal-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/journal-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo Academic&amp;rsquo;s Markdown slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code and math&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example conference paper</title>
      <link>/publication/conference-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/conference-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo Academic&amp;rsquo;s Markdown slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code and math&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
