<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Source Themes | Emanuele Dicarlo</title>
    <link>/tag/source-themes/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/source-themes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Source Themes</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon.png</url>
      <title>Source Themes</title>
      <link>/tag/source-themes/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>How do Firms adjust to Negative Labor Supply Shocks? Evidence form Migration Outflows (Job Market Paper)</title>
      <link>/workinprogress/0migration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/workinprogress/0migration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The quality of workers in a country positively relates to productivity of firms, adoption of new technologies, and growth. This paper studies adjustments of Italian firms to negative labor supply shocks in the context of workers&amp;rsquo; outflows from Italy to Switzerland. My Diff-in-Diff leverages the implementation of a policy in which Switzerland granted free labor market mobility to EU citizens and different treatment intensity of Italian firms based on their distance to the Swiss border. Using detailed social security data on the universe of Italian firms and workers, I document large outflows of workers and fewer surviving firms in the treatment group. Despite replacing workers and becoming more capital intensive, treated firms are less productive and pay lower wages.
I explain this evidence through the lens of a simple production function with high and low-skilled labor. In line with the brain drain literature, I show how adverse effects of large outflows of workers operate through firms that workers leave. I provide suggestive evidence that high-skill intensive firms are the main driver of the negative results on wages and productivity.  I also show that low skill intensive firms instead suffer less from losing workers and provide new job opportunities for the workers who do not migrate.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Season in Hell: Italy’s Debt Recovery after the Financial Crises (joint with P. Rizza and P. Tommasino)</title>
      <link>/workinprogress/2bdi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/workinprogress/2bdi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sorting across the line: evidence from a Tax Discontinuity in Italy (joint with Enrico Rubolino)</title>
      <link>/workinprogress/3satl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/workinprogress/3satl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we plan to investigate whether taxation has distortionary effects on the geographical distribution of the taxpayers. We use a geographical discontinuity in the tax rate of Italian municipalities closer to Switzerland to show whether Italian tax payers relocate on the side where taxes are lower. This question is relevant to any country sharing borders. Countries typically have differential tax rates, and because of the constant increase in the mobility of labor, this could generate relocations of workers with several implications for the affected areas. Depending on the findings of this first stage, we will investigate the effects of a redistribution in tax revenues on several outcomes: local service provision, labor markets, and efficiency of the local administrators.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Skill Content of Occupations across Low and Middle Income Countries: Evidence from Harmonized Data</title>
      <link>/otherwork/0wb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/otherwork/0wb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Using new and harmonized worker-level survey data on tasks at work in the developing
world, this paper constructs, for the first time, a measure of the skill content of occupations
for 10 low and middle-income countries. Following Autor, Levy and Murnane (2003),
Acemoglu and Autor (2011), and Autor and Handel (2013), we map tasks into non-routine
analytical, non-routine interpersonal, and routine &amp;amp; manual skill groups. We find significant
differences in the skill mix used by workers across different occupations, with selected whitecollar occupations being intensive in Analytical and Interpersonal skills, while others— mostly
blue collar, but not only— being more intensive in Routine and Manual skills. We also find
that the rankings of occupations along the skill dimensions are quite stable across countries,
and they correlate significantly higher between middle- and low-income countries than
between them and the United States. Hence, the common practice of assuming the same
skill structure for occupations in the United States and other countries can be misleading.
Finally, we find that the heterogeneity of skill content between occupations (within countries)
tends to decrease with the level of income, while the heterogeneity within occupations
decreases only weakly (or not at all) for higher income levels. Taken together, these results
suggest that as countries develop, they tend to adopt and use certain skills more widely,
especially across occupations. This may suggest some degree of specialization in skills
content of tasks as countries develop, especially moving towards less occupation-specific
Analytical or Interpersonal skills that are becoming increasingly relevant across the board.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
